Strategic Initiative MCCIA, Naval Armament Officials Discuss Defence Testing Centre in Pune In a recent interaction, MCCIA and Naval Armament officials discussed a proposed defence and aerospace testing and qualification centre in Pune to address testing bottlenecks, accelerate indigenisation and strengthen MSME participation in defence supply chains.
A brief report.
MCCIA held a strategic interaction infrastructure and outlined its engagement A dedicated defence and with Cmde Rajesh Chatterjee, with defence manufacturers.
A key issue raised aerospace testing centre in Controllerate of Naval Armament, during the discussion was the limited and Pune could reduce testing and Lt Com Siddharth K, Naval fragmented access to specialised testing and Armament, along with senior MCCIA qualification facilities required by private- bottlenecks, accelerate representatives, to discuss specialised sector companies developing naval, defence product qualification and testing infrastructure, indigenisation, and aerospace products.
support faster indigenisation MSME capability development and global supply-chain opportunities for Pune and Existing Testing Capability for defence manufacturers Presented Maharashtra’s defence manufacturing sector.
and MSMEs.
The meeting also explored a proposal for a MCCIA briefed the Naval Armament comprehensive defence and aerospace testing officials on the Electronics Common Facility and qualification centre in the Pune region.
Centre at Bhosari, established with support During the interaction, MCCIA from MeitY.
The facility houses a 10-metre presented its existing industry-support semi-anechoic EMI/EMC chamber august 2026 | SAMPADA | 47
capable of vehicle-level testing and deep tech.
The meeting underlined the need for closer collaboration among industry, enables companies to undertake activities for continued collaboration among industry, government and defence establishments to ranging from concept development and government and defence establishments to strengthen indigenous capabilities, improve prototyping to international testing, expand indigenous manufacturing capabilities.
access to specialised infrastructure and enable certification and manufacturing.
more MSMEs to participate in advanced The Chamber also presented its wider Towards a Stronger Defence defence manufacturing.
Such coordinated Ecosystem support network covering more than efforts can support the development of a more 3,500-member organisations across 21 The interaction also looked beyond competitive, technology-driven and selfsectoral verticals.
MCCIA also outlined the testing infrastructure to explore opportunities reliant defence manufacturing ecosystem in work of its Defence Committee, established for connecting Maharashtra’s MSMEs Pune and Maharashtra.
in 1999, and its engagement with the with global defence and aerospace supply l armed forces.
This includes its partnership chains through international platforms and with the 512 Army Base Workshop, Kirkee, partnerships.
These discussions form part of for vendor identification, fabrication and MCCIA’s wider plans to develop Centres of indigenisation of spares.
Excellence in frontier technologies including AI, smart manufacturing, semiconductors, Scan the QR code to Testing Centre Proposal land systems, space and deep tech.
listen to the gist of the Discussed The dialogue highlighted the need article.
The meeting identified access to specialised testing and qualification facilities as a significant bottleneck for Criss Cross Answer private defence manufacturers.
Naval systems and ammunition components require shock, vibration, reliability and other qualification testing, while facilities currently available across different institutions can result in longer development and procurement cycles.
Against this background, the participants discussed the possibility of establishing a dedicated defence and aerospace testing and qualification centre in the Pune region.
The proposed centre could provide more integrated access to testing infrastructure, support faster product development and qualification and facilitate indigenisation.
The possibility of leveraging MIDC land and State or Central Government support was also discussed.
Global Supply Chains Explored The interaction also considered ways to connect Maharashtra’s MSMEs with international defence and aerospace supply chains through global platforms and partnerships.
The discussion was aligned with MCCIA’s plans to establish Centres of Excellence in frontier technology areas including AI, smart manufacturing, semiconductors, land systems, space and 48 | SAMPADA | august 2026
This article is from Sampada, published by MCCIA.